Finding Aid for Dorothy Gies McGuigan Papers 1938-1982
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dorothy Gies McGuigan papers 1938-1982, 1970-1982
McGuigan, Dorothy Gies.
1 linear feet
Historian, instructor at the University of Michigan, program director at the Center for the Education of Women. Research files on historical topics and gender issues; lectures and conference papers; files relating to her involvement with the Alice and Edith Hamilton Award given for the best manuscript dealing with some facet of women's lives.
0223 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Elizabeth M. Douvan (donor no. 9071 ) and came to the library in 2001.
The collection is open for research.
Dorothy Gies McGuigan, born Dorothy Gies on November 12, 1914, received her Master of Arts from the department of English and comparative literature at Columbia University in 1939. Her thesis was entitled, "Women and Undisclosed Writing during the Restoration Period in England." Throughout her life she maintained her interest in historical research, particularly Austrian history, publishing The Habsburgs (1966) and Metternich and the Duchess (1975). McGuigan also continued to work on her masters thesis which she intended to publish as "Printers, Peddlers, Politicians: Women in Literary Trades: 1500-1700."
McGuigan came to the University of Michigan in 1955 as an instructor teaching business writing in the school of business administration, later in 1974, she was appointed lecturer in the English department. She also taught in the Residential College. While at the University, McGuigan was program director and editor at the Center for the Education of Women (formerly the Center of the Continuing Education of Women). While at the CEW she was able to pursue her interests in gender issues and women in higher education, and to "work to help women reach achievements beyond their expectations" (CEW scholarship descriptions). She published A Dangerous Experiment: 100 Years of Women at the University of Michigan (1970). She also edited Women's Lives: New Theory, Research, and Policy Issues: Papers from the Conference Held November 1979.
McGuigan was a driving force behind the Women's Studies Program and a founding member of the editorial board of the University Press series on Women and Culture series and the Alice and Edith Hamilton Award. The Women and Culture series was designed to encourage excellence in the new women's scholarship, to add stature and coherence to the field of women's studies, and to serve as a stimulus to younger scholars to research and write in these areas. The Hamilton award, funded by Horace Rackham Graduate School and the Alumni Office, was given for the best scholarly book-length manuscript dealing with some facet or facets of women's lives past or present. The award was named for Alice Hamilton, an alumnus of the University of Michigan Medical School (1893) and a pioneer in environmental medicine, and her sister Edith, a celebrated classics scholar and author of The Greek Way who taught at the University during the 1920s. Toward the end of her life, McGuigan helped to create the Committee for Gender Research to encourage research on gender issues.
Dorothy McGuigan died in October 1982. In 1983 the Center for the Education of Women created a scholarship in her name designed to recognize women pursuing their interest in women's studies or related fields.
The papers of Dorothy McGuigan consist primarily of materials relating to her work and scholarly interests while at the University of Michigan. The most heavily documented areas of the collection pertain to her research and to her involvement with the Alice and Edith Hamilton Award at the University Michigan. The collection has been divided into five series: Scholarly Work, Lectures and Conference Papers, Research, the Alice and Edith Hamilton Award, and Organizational Affiliations and Interests.
Subjects:
Alice and Edith Hamilton Award (University of Michigan); Behn, Aphra, 1640-1689.; Feminists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; McGuigan, Dorothy Gies.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Alice and Edith Hamilton Award (University of Michigan); McGuigan, Dorothy Gies.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Scholarly Work
  The Scholarly Work series (1938-1982) includes both published and unpublished papers written by McGuigan. These writings span her career from her time as a graduate student at Columbia University to her employment at the University of Michigan. This series also includes correspondence regarding McGuigan's application for a grant to expand and publish a paper based on her masters thesis, "Women and Undisclosed Writing during the Restoration Period in England", as well as correspondence with her thesis advisor Dr. W. Y. Tindall.
  - Masters Thesis 1938-1973 (Box 1)
  - Letters re. Grant 1975-1980 (Box 1)
  - "Printers, Peddlers, Politicians" (Box 1)
  - "Athena in the Closet" (Box 1)
- Lectures and Conference Papers
  The Lectures and Conference Papers series (1971-1979) provides examples of the lectures, talks, and conference papers that McGuigan gave while at the University of Michigan. The series includes a paper that McGuigan gave at the Wayne State "We, the Women" conference in 1976 as well as a class lecture and information relating to her speaking engagements at the Women's Research Club.
  - Class Lecture-History of Education of Women (Box 1)
  - "The Entrance of Women into the Literary Trade" (Box 1)
  - "Higher Education of Women in Michigan" Presented at Wayne State Conference: "We, the Women" on June 13, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Talk(s) Given at Women's Research Club 1971-1979 (Box 1)
- Research
  The Research series (1969-1982) includes papers related to McGuigan's research and details some of her academic interests. The highlight of this series are McGuigan's writings on women printers Mary Astell, Aphra Behn, and Maria de la Riviera Manley (conceivably for her paper "Printer, Peddlers, Politicians: Women in Literary Trades: 1500-1700"). The series also includes McGuigan's correspondence with Betty Eisenstein, Werner Gundersheimer, Paul Kristeller, and Edna Steeves, other scholars with similar interests.
  - Research Assistance 1976-1980 (Box 1)
  - Writings on Individuals
    - Astell, Mary (Box 1)
    - Behn, Aphra (Box 1)
    - Manley, Maria de la Riviera (Box 1)
  - Interest Files
    - Academic Discrimination 1970 (Box 1)
    - Art and Women's Needlework 1972 (Box 1)
    - Equal Rights Amendment and the Committee to Establish a Commission on the Status of Women 1970-1973 (Box 1)
    - History of Women and General 1970-1978 (Box 1)
    - Honorary Doctorate for Jean Campbell, Director of CCEW 1971-1980 (Box 1)
    - Law Schools 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - Marriage and Family / Abortion and Birth Control 1970 (Box 1)
    - Women's International League for Peace and Freedom 1982 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Other Scholars
    - Eisenstein, Mrs. Julian (Betty) 1973 (Box 1)
    - Gundersheimer, Werner / Kristeller, Paul 1978-1979 (Box 1)
      (also concerns Goggio Bartolommeo)
    - Steeves, Edna 1972-1973 (Box 1)
      (relates in part to a controversy about feminism)
- Alice and Edith Hamilton Award
  The Alice and Edith Hamilton Award series (1975-1982) documents both McGuigan's involvement in the award's advisory committee and the history both of the award itself and the University of Michigan Press Women and Culture Series. The series includes correspondence between the advisory committee members, prospectuses and circulation reports, and minutes of board meetings, as well as correspondence between McGuigan and the first recipients of the Hamilton Award, Estelle Freedman and Valerie Pichanick, and between McGuigan and other University offices regarding the award.
  - History-Hamilton Award and UM Press Women and Culture Series 1975-1980 (Box 1)
  - Award Winners
    - First Hamilton Award Winners 1979 (Box 1)
    - Photos 1980, undated (Box 1)
  - Advisory Board 1978-1982, 4 folders (Box 1)
- Organizational Affiliations and Interests
  The last series, Organizational Affiliations and Interests (1970-1982), provides an account of McGuigan's other affiliations and interests during her time at the University of Michigan. The most heavily documented are those files pertaining to McGuigan's involvement in the Committee for Gender Studies (also the Committee for Gender Research). The collection also includes files detailing her involvement and interest in the editorial board of LSA magazine, the University of Michigan Women's Calendar, and a television show, entitled "Women Today: Images, Realities," produced by the University of Michigan Television Center.
  - Committee for Gender Studies 1978-1982, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - National Symposium for Women and Peace, Proposal for 1980-1982 (Box 1)
  - Women and Religion Conference 1981 (Box 1)
  - LSA Magazine Editorial Board 1979 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Television Center 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Women's Calendar 1982 (Box 1)